Guide to the Ruth Alice Haas Papers MS 033
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Ruth Alice Haas Papers
1922-1987
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Haas, Ruth A., 1903-1986.
MS 033
23.5 Linear Feet, 16 boxes and 1 OS Folder
Ruth Alice Haas (1903-1986) arrived the Danbury Normal School in 1931 to serve as Dean of Women. For fifteen years, she lived in Fairfield Hall as the primary mentor and supervisor for boarding students. Over the years, she assumed more responsibility. In 1946, after President Jenkins' death, she was the unanimous choice for president. She served as president for twenty-eight years, through times of significant growth and change for the school. These papers contain a cross section of her administrative records and her personal papers.
12 linear feet (12 boxes)
Provenance
Provenance not documented.
Access Restrictions
Series 2, Appointment Papers and Resignations, closed to researchers.
Historical/Biographical Note
Ruth Alice Haas was born on March 30, 1903, in Syracuse, New York. She attended schools in Syracuse and Amherstberg, Ontario, Canada, and earned a B.S. in education and a M.A. in political science from Syracuse University. Before coming to Danbury, she taught in Watertown, New York, and in the Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs at Syracuse University
Ruth Haas came to the Danbury Normal School as Dean of Women in 1931. She was appointed President of Danbury State Teachers College in 1946 thus becoming the first woman in the United States to serve as president of a four-year state college.
During her tenure as president, she served as President of the Eastern States Association of Professional Schools for Teachers, President of the Connecticut Council on Higher Education, and President of the New England Association of Teachers Colleges. She also served on the New England Board of Higher Education, the Advisory Council to the Connecticut Commission on Higher Education, and on the State Commission on Cooperation with Federal Authorities in Matters Pertaining to Higher Education.
In Danbury, Ruth Haas served as a Manager and a Trustee of Danbury Hospital, as a Trustee of the Danbury Library, as a Trustee of the Scott-Fanton Museum and as a member of the Bicentennial Commission. She was a recipient of the News Times Civic Achievement Award, the first to receive the Book of Golden Deeds award of the Exchange Club, and received the Liberty Bell Award from the Danbury Bar Association.
Ruth Haas received many honors, awards and citations throughout her career and in 1969 the new library at Western Connecticut State College was named in her honor. She also received honorary degrees from Syracuse University, Rhode Island College, Albertus Magnus College, and the University of Hartford. Ruth Haas died on November 25, 1986.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ruth A. Haas consist of materials that document her education and her career at Danbury State College.
Series 1 contains RAH's education and honorary degrees which consist of The Annual, Watertown High School's 1925 yearbook, where Haas taught history for several years, and Syracuse University's 1922 and 1924 yearbook The Onondagan. Also included are RAH's B. A. and M.S., as well as her master's thesis, and several honorary degrees.
Series 2, 4, 5, and 7 document RAH's appointment as president of Danbury State Teacher's College and inauguration. These series contain invitations, inauguration program, clippings and news releases, and The Inkling, a campus newsletter, which covered the inauguration as well RAH's keynote speech to the 21st Eastern States Association's Conference on March 21-23, 1947. Also included is an autograph letter (signed) addressed to Haas from Eleanor Roosevelt declining an invitation to attend the Conference.
Correspondence from governors and other political figures include John David Lodge, Mrs. Francis W. Cole, Thomas J. Meskill, John Alsop, Lowell P. Weicker, Jr., Florence D. Finney, Ruth O. Truex, Robert K. Killian, George E. Steinmetz, Romeo E. Petroni, Ella Grasso, S. McLellan, Henry E. Parker, Nancy Lewinsohn, William R. Baldwin, and Dr. Harvey S. Sadow.
Among RAH's Personal Papers there is an address, Amherstburg, delivered by F.W. Haas, RAH's father, to the members of the Lake Erie and St. Clair Publishers' Association on October 12, 1928. The address, in a small booklet form, was a brief survey of historical Amhertsburg and Old Fort Malden. Other papers in this folder include a copy of her birth certificate, retirement papers, and a farewell letter addressed to her college family dated May 8, 1975, before her retirement.
In 1966, Haas was the first recipient of the Golden Deeds Award presented by the Exchange Club of Danbury for her contribution to higher education in Connecticut. Included among the papers are congratulatory letters and telegrams from family, friends, and business leaders in the community, as well as the program and clippings of the event. Among the many individuals who sent congratulatory letters and cards were Walter Werner, Bert Stroock, Harold Hodgdon, Jr., Howard Holmes, Abe and Bertha Feinson, William H. Flaharty, John Hoffer, Edward Sillari, John Monagan, William Sanders, Abe Ribicoff, Richard Rausch, Fay Overholt, Carl and Ruth Denison, Kathryn Vacha, Max Levy, Mary Swokla, Abe Ribicoff, Frank and Mabel Palermo; Patrick Cahilll; Fritz, Fritzi, and Joseph (RAH's sister and family); and the faculty of DSC.
Correspondence in celebration of Haas' 25th anniversary as president of DSC consist of congratulatory letters from family members, friends, colleagues, local clubs and organizations. Correspondents include Warren G. Hill, Bobbi Pough, Romeo Petroni, William R. Ratchford, Lowell P. Weicker, Jr., John S. Monagan, Ella T. Grasso, Thomas J.Meskill, Clark Hull, William J. Sanders, Regina, Dick, Manson Van Jennings, Hilton C. Buley, Herbert D. Welte, Marguerite Paatchen, Chester E. Floyd, Raymond Trimpert, Ernest A. Johnson, Dorothy Hutton Shippee, John Lyman, Hazel D. Tobias, Esther E. Wagner, Fayette L. Overholt, Finis E. Engleman, and John Lyman.
Haas was also honored by the Danbury Chamber of Commerce on her 25th anniversary and was given a silver tray commemorating the event. A copy of the invitation and program for the event are also included. Additional honors came from the House of Representatives when a resolution, presented by John S. Monagan of Connecticut, was passed honoring Haas for her 25 years of service as WCSC president. A copy of the Congressional Record speech as well as a transcript of a WINE salute to Haas by Ron Gleissner on March 9, 1972.
Retirement testimonials and honors includes notes and letters from Daniel J. Flood, Regina M. Duffy, Seymour R. Powers, Owen F. Peagler, Mildred Lucas, Harold P. Splain, Herbert S. Everett, H. B. Schramm, Robert M. Beatty, Leonard J. Kent, Everett I. L. Baker, A. M. Woodruff, Arthur C. Banks, Jr., Louis Rabineau, Richard C. Gurney, Pearl Griska, Clint Walker, Walter J. Conn, Roger B. Bagley, Donald H. McGannon, David Detzer, and Sister Mary Theodore. In addition, two Book of Letters were presented to Haas at her retirement from Colleagues and Friends, and the Alumni Association. Also included is a guest book and program from her testimonial dinner (box 3).
Series 2 also contains minutes of the meetings of state college presidents that cover a number of issues pertaining to the operation of a four-college campus. Topics include administrative issues, budgets, salary schedules, tuition, increased enrollment, course offerings, faculty, and building projects. In addition, this series contains appointment papers of former employees, salaries and yearly budgets from 1949-1973. The bulk of the budgets in this series were created during RAH's tenure as President, but there are also budgets, as well as appointment papers, resignations, and salaries, created by her predecessors. The budgets after WW II reflect DSTC's tremendous growth from a two building college with 125 students to a nine building college campus with a broad liberal arts curriculum with over 5,000 students. Please note that Series 2, Appointment Papers and Resignations, (folders 7-43), are closed to researchers.
Photographs that document special events and anniversaries for Haas are located in Series 4. Included are images of her 25th anniversary celebration in 1972, retirement testimonial in 1975, receiving an honorary degree from Alberta Magnus College is 1973, groundbreaking of Ella Grasso Hall in 1981, and studio portraits for her inauguration. Images also include school faculty, state politicians, and friends at these events.
Series 5 contains two scrapbooks, one of which was created by RAH's sister, Fredericka Haas Batchelor, that contains telegrams, letters, photographs, and newspaper articles of RAH's 1947 inauguration, while the other contains newspaper articles that focus on the tremendous growth of the school from a two building Normal School to a seven building campus under the helm of RAH. Articles include increased enrollment, changes in curriculum and degrees, as well as RAH's 25th anniversary and retirement.
Series 6 contain condolence letters and notes sent to Fredericka Batchelor, niece of RAH, upon her aunt's death as well as the funeral guest book.
Series 7 includes miscellaneous memorabilia such as yearbooks, postcards, plaques, and gavel.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically or chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 7 series:
Missing Title
Education and Honorary Degrees,
Danbury State Teacher's College
Certificates/Recognitions/Resolutions,
Photographs,
Scrapbooks,
Funeral, and,
Miscellaneous Memorabilia.
Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Ephemera.; Danbury (Conn.); Correspondence.; Budgets.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Western Connecticut State University; Danbury Teachers College.; Danbury State Teachers College.; Western Connecticut State College -- History.; Haas, Ruth A., 1903-1986.
- 1. Education and Honorary Degrees
  - The Onondagan, 1922, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Annual, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Master's Thesis, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Syracuse University Master's Degree, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rhode Island College of Education (Honorary Degree - Ed.D.), 1947 (Box OS1, Folder *)
  - Syracuse University (Honorary Degree LL.D), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albertus Magnus College (Honorary Degree LL.D), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - University of Hartford (Honorary Degree DD.L), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Syracuse University Alumni News, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 2. Danbury State Teacher's College
  - Minutes of State Colleges Presidents' Meetings
    - Minutes, 1957, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - DSC Samples of Student Evaluation of Credits, 1940-1957 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - DSC Sample of Registration and Credit Record (Margaret E. Lathrop), 1929-1945 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Appointment Papers - Former Employees, 1935-1964 (w/gaps)
    - A-B, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - C-D, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Ec, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Ed, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - El-En, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - En, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Fa-Fe, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Fi, undated (Box 7, Folder 8-11)
    - Fl-Fo, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Ga-Ge, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Gi, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Gl-Gr, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Gr, undated (Box 7, Folder 16-19)
    - Han, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Han-Har, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Har-Hay, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Hen, undated (Box 7, Folder 23-24)
    - Hi-Ho, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Ho-Hu, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Hu, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - I, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Ja, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Je, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Ji, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Jo, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Ka-Ke, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Ki-Kl, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - M-N, undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - O-R, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - S-T, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - V-Z, undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Resignations, 1934-1965 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Salaries: Danbury Normal School and Training School Teachers (Locust and Balmforth Avenue schools, Miry Brook and Kindergarten)
    - Salaries, 1923-1924 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Salaries, 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Salaries, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Salaries, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Salaries, 1928-1929 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Salaries, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - DSC Faculty (Salaries, education, committees), 1963 (Box OS6, Folder *)
  - Budgets
    - Biennial Budget, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Budget, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Budget, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - Budget, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
    - Biennial Budget, 1953-1955 (Box 9, Folder 3-5)
    - Budget, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    - Budget, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - Budget, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Budget, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
    - Biennial Budget, 1957-1959 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Budget, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Budget, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Biennial Budget, 1959-1961 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Budget, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
    - Budget, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
    - Biennial Budget, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Budget, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
    - Budget, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Budget, Surpluses, Capital Costs, Dorm Finances (w/gaps), 1929-1963 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Budget, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 29-30)
    - Biennial Budget, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Proposed Budget, State System of Higher Education, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Budget, 1966- 1967 (Box 6, Folder 33-34)
    - Biennial Budget, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 35-38)
    - Budget, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 40-41)
    - Biennial Budget, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Budget, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Budget, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Budget, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 44-45)
    - Budget, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 46-47)
  - Inauguration, 25th Anniversary, Retirement
    - Inauguration, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Appointment Books, 1961-1963, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder *)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Personal Papers, 1962-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Exchange Club of Danbury, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Commencement Programs, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Commencement Address, January 26, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Material for Talks, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 25th Anniversary, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Personality Profile with Dr. Ruth Haas, Sunday, March 19, 1972 by radio station WLAD Danbury (audio tape) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Retirement - Testimonial Letters, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Retirement Program, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Retirement - Congressional Record, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Retirement - Book of Letters from her Colleagues and Friends Book I - June 6, 1975 (Box 3, Folder *)
    - Retirement - Book of Letters from the Alumni Association Book II - June 6, 1975 (Box 3, Folder *)
    - Retirement - Book of Letters (loose pages), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Retirement - Guest Book, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Retirement - A Tribute to Ruth Haas as recorded Friday, June 6, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- 3. Certificates, Recognitions & Resolutions
  - AAUW, The Danbury Area Branch, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AAUW Education Foundation (framed), 1975 (Box 5, Folder *)
  - Connecticut Assn. for the Advancement of School Administrators, undated (Box OS1, Folder *)
  - Connecticut Council on Higher Education (framed), 1975 (Box OS2, Folder *)
  - Connecticut, State of, Joint House Resolutions (framed), 1972, 1975 (Box OS2, Folder *)
  - Connecticut State University Resolution (framed), 1987 (Box OS2, Folder *)
  - Danbury Chamber of Commerce (Silver Tray), March 25, 1972 (Box OS5, Folder *)
  - Danbury Commission on the Status of Women, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Delta Kappa Gamma Society Membership Certificate, undated (Box 5, Folder *)
  - Exchange Club's Book of Golden Deeds Award (plaque), undated (Box OS2, Folder *)
  - First Book of Golden Deeds Award, (program) June 4, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Higher Education Center for Urban Studies, 1975 (Box OS1, Folder *)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rotary Club of Newtown, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rotary International, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - WCSC Board of Trustees Resolution, June 13, 1975 (Box OS6, Folder *)
  - WCSC Student Body Medal/Commemoration, 1975 (Box 5, Folder *)
- 4. Photographs
  - Photographs, Convocation, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, Commencements, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Photographs, 25th Anniversary, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Photographs, Alberta Magnus College, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Photographs, Retirement, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Photographs, Groundbreaking/Westside Campus, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photographs, Portraits, undated (Box OS4, Folder *)
- 5. Scrapbooks
  - Clippings, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings (created by Fredericka Haas Batchelor), 1947-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 6. Funeral
  - Funeral Guest Book, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Condolences (cards and notes), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Condolences (letters), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- 7. Memorabilia
  - Alumni Board tribute honoring Dr. Ruth A. Haas (framed 11.5x17), 1975 (Box OS3, Folder *)
  - Collage of achievements (framed and mounted on wood), undated (Box 5, Folder *)
  - Gavel: "E.S.A.T.E. President Dr. Ruth A. Haas" (Eastern States Association of Professional Schools for Teachers), 1947 (Box 5, Folder *)
  - Lasell Leaves, 1921 (Box 5, Folder *)
  - The Magazine for Connecticut Living, "Wesconn Revisited", 1973 (Box 5, Folder *)
  - Plaque: With Sincere Gratitude Class of 1953, undated (Box 5, Folder *)
  - Portrait of Ruth Haas presented by the Class of 1967 (framed), undated (Item 01, Folder *)
  - Postcards: Campus Buildings, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Quilt presented to RAH upon retirement (origin unknown), undated (Box OS7, Folder *)
  - Tribute to a Great Lady by Jim Dyer, 1975 (Box OS7, Folder *)
  - WCSC Yearbooks, 1975, 1978 (Box OS7, Folder *)
  - YMCA Century Club Plaque, undated (Box OS7, Folder *)
  - Fredericka Batchelor, Obituary, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - New York Times, June 18, 1935 (Folder OS 1)